so we'll do a suture reading now and
like a little commentary we can go
passage by passage
before that
if you read the entire sutta it's going
to be linked in the description
of this video so read it beforehand and
then come back to the video so that that
you can follow
everything that's being said
so it's a
marketable the monkey it's in
sangitanikaya and it starts like this
and it starts like this
because in the himalayas the king of
mountains there are rugged and uneven
zones where neither monkeys nor human
beings can go there are rugged and
uneven zones where monkeys can go but no
human beings can go
and there are even and delightful
regions where both monkeys and human
beings can go
there along the monkey trails hunters
set out traps for catching monkeys those
monkeys who are not foolish and
frivolous when they see the trap avoided from afar
when they see the trap avoided from afar
but a monkey who is foolish and
frivolous approaches the trap and sees
it seizes it with his hand he gets
caught there thinking i will free my
hand and then he seizes it with his
other hand then he gets caught there
thinking i will free both hands he
seizes it with his foot then he gets
caught there
thinking i will free both hands and my
foot he sees it with his other foot and
he gets caught there
thinking i will free both hands and feet
he applies his muzzle to it and he gets
caught there
thus the beak was trapped because that
monkey trapped at five points
lies there screeching he has met with
calamity and disaster and the hunter can
do with him as he wishes the hunter
spares him fastens into that some block
of wood
and goes off where he wants
so it is because when one strays outside
one's own resort into the domain of
others therefore because they're not straight
therefore because they're not straight
outside of your own resort into the main
of others mara will gain access to those
who stray outside of their own resort
into the domain of others
mara will get hold on them
these are the five codes of central
pleasure so it's important to note here
because often
uh often people might
not necessarily realize the extent
of the central pleasure this
that the suit would generally be
describing um so it's not all the sights and sounds
um so it's not all the sights and sounds
and smells and taste and touches because
people would assume aha everything i see
is thus sensuality everything i hear is
the sensuality thus i must stop seeing
everything and hearing everything
no it's the particular
site sounds melted touches
as it says here
that recognizable by the eye ear nose
and so on that are desirable
lovely agreeable enticing
enticing pleasure
lust and wanting more of it
so it's important to to recognize that
you don't need to say no to everything
and like you know stop seeing things and
stop hearing that's impossible
and there are many suitors that would
have said that would fall into the wrong
view and wrong practice
but you need to take responsibility for
acting towards and intending and
welcoming entertaining
things that are agreeable
so it's really the agreeability of
saitan's middle face touches that's the
trap not saitan's military statues
it's it's the
the sites for example that
come that you come across in the world
that then
you find agreeable which is still kind
of part of the site so agree you don't
need to remove the agreeability either
like the trap that hunter sets there
it's fine if it's left alone if the
monkey doesn't touches it there is no
issue doesn't matter how sophisticated
the trap is how agreeable the bait is
how you know
enticing its smell and visual the whole
the whole the whole part of their trap
doesn't matter how
how much um effort has been put into it
for you to be trapped you can't get
trapped unless you reach it with your
hand so unless the monkey goes with it goes
so unless the monkey goes with it goes
for it
no no trap can get it on get him on its
own and that's the point so it's removing
and that's the point so it's removing
the welcoming
and the lighting in the agreeability of
sight sound smell test touches
so developing the mind
to the extent necessary to not act on
impulse upon
seeing hearing smelling tasting touching
things that are agreeable
and uh
and that's if that's if that's developed
sufficiently then you will be able to leave these
then you will be able to leave these
traps alone so the traps will just
remain standing there in the world and
the hunter cannot see you anymore
because you are not uh
getting trapped you're not uh you're not
reaching for the things that they're
outside of your domain and then the
hunter cannot see you and cannot do what
he pleases with you
so that's the
important point to recognize that
it's not about removing all the sense
objects it's about taking responsibility for
it's about taking responsibility for
acting towards them
[Music] through taking on the virtue and sense
through taking on the virtue and sense
restrained
and then basically learning and training
your mind to be able to
not welcome
and delight
in those sites and smell this touches
that are of agreeable nature
then in the agreeable disagreeable and
disagreeably just agreeable they're just
disagreeable there is neither
lasting towards agreeable nor is there
aversion and resistance towards
disagreeable so the mind will be peaceful if that is
so the mind will be peaceful if that is
sufficiently developed
[Music] so then the buddha carries on saying
so then the buddha carries on saying
the same thing so move in your own
resort because
in your own ancestral domain mara will
not gain access to those
who move in their own resort and in
their own ancestral domain mara will not
get a hold of them and what because is
this resort of yours
resort of yours
what is your own ancestral domain it is
the for establishment of mindfulness so
it's the four reference point of that
peripheral awareness that we talk about
they will that would sustain the context
of whether agreeable whether
disagreeable is present there whether
there is a trap
in front of you you will not lose the
sight that it is a trap you will not
forget that it is a trap
and the clearer
your discernment of the danger of the
trap becomes
uh the easier will be to not reach out
for it so you reach out for the tram a
monkey reaches for the trap when he
ignores the danger or if he's completely
unaware of the danger so
even if you become aware of the danger
you might become careless and frivolous
as the sutter says and then you forget
about the danger
and then you think well you'll handle
you'll handle it you know i'll handle
the hunter and so on
failing to understand that any any
contact with the trap implies the the
ultimate imminent danger of death
basically if the mind is
within the domain of sensuality that
doesn't belong to it if the death occurs
at that time as the suitors would say
uh that's that's why the
dying experience of dying experience of
death experience of the cessation of the
senses will be extremely painful and
unpleasant if the mind is withdrawn from
the domain of the senses when those
senses break apart the mind will not be
perturbed by that so that's that
imminent um
[Music] kind of in universal
kind of in universal
danger that's uh
that's inherent in every in every um
in every sense and every trap however
little however small however
insignificant it still carries the same
nature of the same danger
so four foundations of mindfulness
basically means thoroughly established
in four reference points whereby you
cannot forget forget
ignore
and become frivolous and careless in
regard to the obvious danger of
going down the pathways of your five
senses and accepting the agreeability of it and
and accepting the agreeability of it and
enjoying the pleasures that come as a
result of it
so these four reference points
would mean the context will remain
established throughout of them
throughout them regardless of which
referent point reference point is kind
of currently established
the the same context will endure through
it the context of discernment of that
danger and the in the right order as we
said so many times
so this is that resort that uh
a mind can't find safety in and that's
pretty much what what nirvana is like um
as we said many times before
it's not an ibana is not you know
a mystical experience or a special kind
of
um phenomena that will wait for you at
the end
of your practice like a magical
revelation or something nibana is this
very thing establishing yourself
in the
resort of safety withdrawn from
sensuality uh that
uh that
does not fuel passion and aversion
further and it will make them sort of evaporate
and it will make them sort of evaporate
and dissipate if you if you stay in that
safe resort so once
you have spent sufficient amount of time
in that properly established mindfulness
and the right view
your mind will cool down
cool down of passion cool down of
perversion cool down of resistance cool
down of patiga cool down of wrong views
and wrong assumptions and that's what
exactly nirvana is cooling down the
literal meaning of nirvana
so if mindfulness is sustained
correctly that results in a in a thorough
that results in a in a thorough
discernment and knowledge of the danger
and withdrawal
from things that are not yours from the
domains that don't belong to you that
are set as traps pramata
then that will be the experience of
nirvana and um
so for as long as a person
has their
functioning faculties and intelligence
such experience is possible for everyone
to develop